Papers of Reverend Samuel Orcutt
Bridgeport History Center, Bridgeport Public Library
Papers of Reverend Samuel Orcutt
1844-1893
Orcutt, Samuel, 1824-1893
BHC-MSS 0032
1.251 linear feet 3 boxes
Bridgeport History Center, Bridgeport Public Library
One of the greatest resources on the city's history at the Bridgeport History Center is the work of Reverend Samuel Orcutt, who wrote one of the first major histories (1886) of Bridgeport. Within his papers are correspondence as well as the research notes he used in creating this important work.
Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Unknown
Biography
Reverend Samuel Orcutt was born sometime around 1824 to James Orcutt and Salina Crosby in Albany, New York. Orcutt is best known for his extensive history of Bridgeport and outlying areas, Bridgeport and Vicinity, a key text that the Bridgeport History Center refers to again and again.
Orcutt became a minister in the Methodist Episcopal Church, and he preached in New York City and Long Island. A freak train accident ended his life in 1893.
Other works written by Orcutt include histories of Wolcott, Torrington, New Milford, Derby, Connecticut, and the Native Americans of the Housatonic Valley.
Scope and Content of Collection
Most of the material within the papers of Reverend Orcutt collection relate to his work on the histories of Bridgeport and Stratford, Connecticut, although most of the notes are undated. They include gravestone transcriptions, genealogical notes, and other general historical notes that he used in his later works. There are also letters, mostly from the 1870s onwards.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series: the first relates to Orcutts life and primarily contains correspondence. Series II focuses on his general research for the various histories he wrote. The third series is dedicated to the genealogy of the Tomlinson family, due to the extent of material.
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Orcutt, Samuel, 1824-1893; Bridgeport (Conn.); Stratford (Conn.); Tomlinson Family
- Series I, Correspondence and life information
  - Correspondence, 1844-1890 (Box 1, Folder 1-16)
  - Correspondence, 1892-1893 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
- Series II, General Research
  - Accounts, 1880-1889 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Commission from American Home Mission, 1874 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Naugatuck Railroad Passes, 1879-1880 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Obituary clippings, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Genealogy notes, Stratford, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Genealogy notes, Tomlinson and Thompson families, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Genealogy notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 11-13)
  - Other historical notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Gravestone transcriptions, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - History of Stratford and Bridgeport printing, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Sermons and religion notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Engravings, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Portraits of Orcut, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Gravestone of Orcutt, after, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Series III, Tomlinson Family Genealogy
  - Tomlinson genealogy, undated (Box 2, Folder 21-23)
  - Tomlinson genealogy correspondence, 1887-1891 (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
  - Tomlinson genealogy, notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Notes on Tomlinson family, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Tomlinson genealogy, 2nd rough draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Tomlinson genealogy, 3rd rough draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Tomlinson genealogy, printed copy, uncut, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Tomlinson genealogy, printed copy, cut, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)